Guide to the Allan Gurganus Papers, 1961-2019 RL.11748
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Allan Gurganus Papers
1961-2019
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Gurganus, Allan, 1947-
RL.11748
65 Linear Feet
Allan Gurganus (1947- ), a gay, white, Southern writer, was born in Rocky Mount, North Carolina. Gurganus trained as a painter, served in the United States Navy during the Vietnam War, then studied at Sarah Lawrence College and the Iowa Writers' Workshop. He later taught writing at Sarah Lawrence College; the Iowa Writers' Workshop; Stanford University; and Duke University. The collection includes the following series: (1) Writings; (2) Correspondence; (3) Personal Papers; (4) Artwork; and (5) Others' Works.
Arrangement
Arrangement follows creator's chronological dates where available. Archivist arranged where dates are not available.
Biographical / Historical
Allan Gurganus (1947- ), a gay, white, Southern writer, was born in Rocky Mount, North Carolina. He trained as a painter at the University of Pennsylvania, and the Pennsylvania Academy of Fine Arts. As punishment for his draft evasion during the Vietnam War, he served as a message decoder in the United States Navy for three years. It was during his time on the USS Yorktown that he began to write. After his military service, he graduated from Sarah Lawrence College where he had studied with Grace Paley. In the Iowa Writers' Workshop at the University of Iowa, Gurganus studied with John Irving, Stanley Elkin, and John Cheever. It was Cheever who sold one of Gurganus's short stories to The New Yorker without his knowledge. "Minor Heroism" became the first story The New Yorker ever published about a homosexual character. Gurganus later taught writing at Sarah Lawrence College; the Iowa Writers' Workshop; Stanford University; and Duke University.
Extensive personal and professional correspondence between Gurganus and his family, friends, and other artists provides insight into how being gay and living in the south shaped his writing. These letters concern both personal and literary matters. Frequently the correspondents commented on each other's recent publications and work, or on projects in progress.
Access Restrictions
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records. Contact Research Services for more information.
Collection contains electronic records that may need to be reformatted. Access copies of electronic records must be accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services for access.
Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
Collection contains potentially sensitive information. Contact Research Services for Access.
Provenance
The Allan Gurganus Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2012-2019.
Collection Overview
The (1) Writings Series is divided into the Books, Novellas and Articles subseries, Uncollected Works subseries, and Addresses and Speeches subseries. Gurganus's writings, collected here as manuscripts, typescripts, and proofs with notes, documenting his development of well-known and critically-acclaimed works. His collected works include White People; The Practical Heart; Plays Well with Others; and, Local Souls. Gurganus's other books and individual stories, essays, and drawings or illustrations related to the titles are included in this Series.
The (2) Correspondence Series is divided into the Chronological Correspondence subseries which consists of letters to and from Gurganus, publishers, and friends, and the Correspondence, Alphabetical by Name subseries is comprised of correspondence between Gurganus and other writers, artists, literary figures, and close friends.
The (3) Personal Papers Series contains Gurganus's family correspondence, documents, many of the books, letters, art and photographs kept in his home. Financial and legal records as well as documentation of his writing career through contracts and royalty statements are also included in this series. The (4) Artwork Series is comprised of doodles, drawings, paintings, and sketches. Series (5) Others' Works, includes books, articles, and typescripts written by friends, students, and others.
Related Materials
Allan Gurganus papers, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University.
Conditions Governing Access
Access restricted: Acc. 2020-0100 requires additional arrangement, description, and/or screening. Contact Research Services for more information.
Authors, American -- 21st century; American literature -- Southern States; American literature -- 20th century; American literature -- Male authors; Authors, American -- Correspondence; College teachers -- United States; Caucasian race in literature; Essays -- 20th century; Gay men -- Southern States; Literature -- History and criticism; American literature -- Manuscripts; Short stories, American -- 20th century; Humorous stories, American -- History and criticism; Drawings (visual works); Pen and ink drawings.; Original illustrations: Engravings, woodcuts, drawings, lithographs; Paintings (visual works); United States -- Navy -- Sea life; Vietnam War, 1961-1975 -- Personal narratives, American; Gays -- North Carolina; Rocky Mount (N.C.) -- History; Taylor, Paul, 1930-; Eatman, George H.; Humphreys, Josephine; Marlette, Doug; Spiro, Ellen; Thorp, Daisy B.; Yaddo (Artists' colony); Smith, Leverett T., Jr.; Paley, Grace
- Writings, 1972-2018; undated
  Conditions Governing Access
  Collection contains electronic records that must be requested through the collection guide and accessed in our reading room. Contact Research Services with questions. Collection contains fragile audiovisual/photographic formats that may need to be reformatted before use. Contact Research Services for access.
  Scope and Contents
  This Series includes writings by Gurganus, and are arranged into the subseries Books, Novellas and Articles; and Addresses and Speeches. The Books subseries is composed chiefly of manuscripts, drafts, typescripts, and proofs of Gurganus's novels, novellas, essays, and articles with the author's notations and revisions, and provides a thorough representation of the development of each. The Uncollected Works subseries contains drafts, copies, proofs, and published works not included in Gurganus's books and novellas. Transcripts of his speeches appear in the Addresses and Speeches subseries.
  - Books, Novellas and Articles, 1972-2014; undated
    This subseries includes the notes, manuscripts, drafts, revisions; correspondence; galleys; proofs; publicity; and reviews related titles of Gurganus's works. Gurganus's early work includes actual 'cut and paste' edits on typewriter drafts before his use of a computer with that same digital ability. They are arranged chronologically where dates are available.
    - Breathing Lessons, 1981-1982; undated
      - Notes and drafts, 1981-1982; undated (Box 1)
        Includes Library of Congress registration correspondence.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1981 (Box 21)
        Includes a signed copy.
    - Good Help, 1987-1988; undated
      Good Help or The Slave's Tale
      - Notes and drafts, 1987; undated; 4 folders (Box 1)
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1988; 3 folders (Box 21)
        Includes a signed copy; and a copy with an inscription to Ted Pewett.
      - Publicity, 1988; undated; 5 folders (Box 1)
        Includes announcements for readings; illustrations; patron list; and articles.
      - Publicity, oversized, 1988 Feb 21 (Box 24)
      - Publicity, 1988 May 30 (Box 25)
      - Reviews, 1988; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All, 1982-2010; undated
      Gurganus's first novel was a New York Times best seller for eight months. The novel was later adapted into a television mini-series, and a stage play.
      - Notes and drafts, 1983-2001; undated; 27 folders (Box 1)
        Includes Jock - The Good American Story.
      - Notes and drafts, undated; 15 folders (Box 2)
        Includes annotated drafts and correspondence with Eddie P; Her Confession - theatrical adaptation. Also includes Under this Very Mall.
      - Proofs and galleys, 1989-1990; 15 folders (Box 2)
        Includes annotated proofs and galleys.
      - Proofs and galleys, 1990-1991; undated; 23 folders (Box 3)
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1992; 4 items (Box 21)
        Includes Italian and German translations.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, oversized, undated (Box 24)
      - Publicity, 1982-1990; undated; 35 folders (Box 3)
        Includes articles; interviews; invitations; and schedules related to publicity.
      - Publicity, 1990-2010; undated; 100 folders (Box 4)
        Includes articles; fliers; and correspondence related to the novel, and the television mini-series.
      - Publicity, 1989-1994; undated; 11 folders (Box 23)
        Includes articles, fliers, and interviews.
      - Publicity, oversized, 1991-2001; 8 folders (Box 24)
        Includes articles about the television mini-series; German articles; and French articles.
      - Publicity, 1989-1999; 11 folders (Box 25)
        Includes newspaper articles; reviews; and fliers.
      - Reviews, 1989-2003; undated; 16 folders (Box 4)
        Includes reviews from the Los Angeles Times; and the Book-of-the-Month Club.
      - Correspondence, 1988; undated; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All, television mini-series, 1994; 4 items (Box 71, Video-cassette RL11748-VHS-0001-RL11748-VHS-0004)
    - White People: Stories and Novellas, 1972-1997; undated
      White People is a collection of stories and novellas including Adult Art; A Hog Loves Its Life; America Competes; Art History; Blessed Assurance; Condolences to Every One of Us; It Had Wings; Minor Heroism; Nativity, Caucasian; and Reassurance.
      - Notes and drafts, artwork, undated (Box 4)
        Includes original artwork for the book.
      - Notes and drafts, 1989-1990; undated; 21 folders (Box 4)
        Includes drafts of Adult Art; A Hog Loves Its Life; America Competes; Art History; Blessed Assurance; and Breathing Room.
      - Notes and drafts, 1972-1997; undated; 40 folders (Box 5)
        Includes annotated drafts and galleys, correspondence, and articles related to Condolences to Every One of Us; It Had Wings, with illustrations; Minor Heroism; Nativity, Caucasian; and Reassurance.
      - Proofs and galleys, 1986-1990; undated; 14 folders (Box 5)
        Includes annotated drafts and galleys, correspondence, and articles related to Blessed Assurance, with a draft of the teleplay by Joyce Eliason; Condolences to Every One of Us; It Had Wings; Minor Heroism, Nativity, Caucasian; and Reassurance. Also included is Blessed Assurance as published in Granta magazine.
      - Proofs and galleys, 1990-1991; 8 folders (Box 6)
        Includes annotated proofs and galleys. Also includes Minor Heroism as published in the New Yorker magazine.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1974; undated; 2 folders (Box 6)
        Includes Nativity, Caucasian, as published in the Brown Journal of the Arts with an inscription to Marvin and Ethel Gurganus.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1990 (Box 21)
        Includes the Spanish translation, Blancos.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 2001 (Box 22)
        Includes the French translation, Les Blancs: Nouvelles.
      - Publicity, 1974-1994; undated; 47 folders (Box 6)
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1989; 2 items (Box 21)
        Includes A Hog Loves Its Life, published in The Quarterly; and Boys Like Us.
      - Publicity, oversized, 1991; 1992; 5 folders (Box 24)
      - Publicity, 1991; 1995; undated; 4 folders (Box 25)
        Includes newspaper reviews, including a review in Spanish published in El País.
      - Publicity, Blessed Assurance, 1991 (Box 23)
      - Publicity, Blessed Assurance, oversized, 1995 Jul 2 (Box 24)
        Includes an article on the television movie, The Price of Heaven, which was adapted from the novella.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works of Nativity, Caucasian, oversized, 1987 (Box 24)
        Includes Nativity, Caucasian which was published in the Village Advocate.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, oversized, 1991 (Box 24)
        Includes Los Angeles Times Book Prizes flier for White People.
      - Nativity, Caucasian, undated (Box 72, Audio-cd RL11748-CD-0002)
        Includes a recording of Gurganus reading Nativity, Caucasian.
      - Reviews, 1991-1992; undated; 18 folders (Box 6)
    - The Biography of My Autobiography, undated
      - Notes and drafts, undated; 3 folders (Box 6)
        Includes annotated drafts.
    - Selections from the Writings of Allan Gurganus on his Fiftieth Birthday, undated
      - Notes and drafts, undated (Box 6)
    - Plays Well With Others, 1991-1998; undated
      Includes annotated drafts and galleys, arranged chronologically where dates are available.
      - Notes and drafts, 1997; 4 folders (Box 6)
        Includes annotated typed manuscripts.
      - Notes and drafts, 1997; undated; 23 folders (Box 7)
        Includes annotated drafts and galleys, including subtitle Thirty Dildoes.
      - Notes and drafts, undated; 19 folders (Box 8)
      - Proofs and galleys, 1997; 6 folders (Box 8)
      - Proofs and galleys, 1997-1998; undated; 13 folders (Box 9)
        Includes a bound, annotated draft.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1997; 1999; 3 items (Box 21)
        Includes the German translation, Die alteste noch lebende Rebellen-witwe erzahlt.
      - Plays Well with Others Proofs and Galleys, 1997; undated (Box 23)
        Includes cover proofs.
      - Publicity, 1991-1999; undated; 19 folders (Box 9)
        Includes interviews, and publicity.
      - Publicity, 1997 (Box 23)
        Includes an interview with Gurganus published in Bomb magazine.
      - Publicity, oversized, 1997; undated; 6 folders (Box 24)
        Includes reviews; interviews; and articles. Also includes a note from Lee Smith.
      - Plays Well With Others audiobook cassettes, 1997; 4 items (Box 72, Audio-cassette RL11748-CS-0001 - RL11748-CS-0004)
        Includes Gurganus reading Plays Well With Others.
      - Reviews, 1997-1998; undated; 21 folders (Box 9)
        Includes interviews, and reviews.
      - Publicity, 2001 Nov 21 (Box 25)
    - Sacrificial Couples and the Splendor of our Failures: Scott and Zelda Fitzgerald, undated
      - Notes and drafts, undated; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - The Practical Heart: Four Novellas, 1974-2009; undated
      This subseries includes materials related to the novellas and chapters in The Practical Heart including: He's One, Too; The Practical Heart; Expense of Spirit; Impractical Truth; Preservation News; Available for Restoration; Celebrating the Life of Theodore Hunstable Worth; Saint Monster - New Testament; and Saint Monster - Old Testament. The materials are arranged chronologically where dates are available.
      - Notes and drafts, 1974-1976; undated; 29 folders (Box 10)
      - Notes and drafts, 2001; undated; 9 folders (Box 11)
        Includes annotated drafts of Preservation News #14; Saint Monster; and Expense of the Heart.
      - Proofs and galleys, 1993; 2001; 20 folders (Box 11)
        Includes annotated proofs, including He's One Too; Old Testament; and cover art in German.
      - Proofs and galleys, 2001; undated; 8 folders (Box 12)
        Includes bound copies of Preservation News; correspondence; and cover art.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1997 (Box 12)
        Includes a bound copy of Preservation News.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 2004; 3 items (Box 22)
        Includes the German translation, Die wilden Jahre.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 2009 (Box 22)
        Includes the Italian translation of Saint Monster, Santo Mostro, with an inscription to Maria.
      - Publicity, 1993-2001; undated; 15 folders (Box 12)
        Includes a cover proof in German; interviews; articles; and publicity.
      - Publicity, oversized, 1998 Mar 29 (Box 24)
        Includes an article on the opera adapted from Practical Heart.
      - Publicity, 1999 (Box 25)
        Includes a performance flier for Practical Heart by The Jewish Museum Program.
      - Reviews, 1998-2001; undated; 10 folders (Box 12)
    - My Heart is a Snake Farm, 2004-2005; undated
      - Notes and drafts, 2004; 4 folders (Box 12)
        Includes a copy of the publication in Harper's magazine.
      - Publicity, 2004 (Box 12)
        Includes an invitation to the Center for Documentary Studies.
      - Publicity, undated (Box 23)
      - Reviews, oversized, 2005 Jun 5 (Box 24)
    - Taletelling the Tyche Collection: Narrative Responses, 2010; undated
      Taletelling the Tyche Collection: Narrative Responses was published in Fortune Smiles: The Tyche Foundation Gift.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 2010; 2 folders (Box 12)
        Includes Taletelling the Tyche Collection: Narrative responses, published in Fortune Smiles; and the Tyche Foundation Collection catalog.
      - Proofs and galleys, undated (Box 23)
        Includes an annotated galley.
    - Local Souls: Novellas, 2012-2016; undated
      Local Souls: Novellas include Decoy; Fear Not; and Saints Have Mothers, and is arranged chronologically where dates are available.
      - Notes and drafts, 2012; undated; 15 folders (Box 12)
        Includes manuscripts with notes; maps of Falls; and editing and production specifications.
      - Notes and drafts, 2015; undated; 24 folders (Box 13)
        Includes annotated drafts of Decoy; and Fear Not.
      - Proofs and galleys, 2012-2013; undated; 10 folders (Box 14)
        Includes correspondence with publishing correspondence.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 2016 (Box 22)
        Includes the Italian translation of Decoy.
      - Proofs and galleys, undated; 4 folders (Box 23)
      - Publicity, 2013; 4 folders (Box 14)
        Includes Local Souls cover art.
  - Uncollected Works, 1973-2014; undated
    This subseries includes drafts; copies; proofs; and published works not included in Gurganus's books, and is arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Notes and drafts, A-C, 1977-2013; undated; 32 folders (Box 14)
      Includes drafts and copies of: $19.95 Walking Tour; A Still Small Voice Under the Cannonade: Field Notes toward Fiction's Pact with History; Allan's Handy Examples; Anatomy of Injustice: Raymond Bonner review; Asheville Takes a Suitor; At My Present Weight; Attempt of a Story About Easter Island; Baseball: Runs Batted In; Basic Photography and the Self-Made Man; Beggars' Etiquette; Behemoth; Billie Holiday research; Blue Devils Made Them Do It; The Body Politic: A Fable; Body Tends to Shine: The Book of Justified Punishments; Boys Like Us, publicity and reviews; The Brussel Sprout as Theology or Food Ways of the Presbyterians; The Business of Blessing; Car Offer; The Case of the Silent Violinist; Charles Dickens' A Christmas Carol; Cholera: We Wish for a Good Young Country Doctor; Chris and Cathy Wilson interview at Old Town Plantation; The Civil War in Us; and A Clean, Well-Lighted Internet Cafe.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 1985; 2 items (Box 21)
        Includes A Body Tends to Shine, published in The Paris Review.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, oversized, 1990 Oct 8 (Box 24)
        Includes The Civil War in Us.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, 2010 (Box 22)
        Includes 27 Views of Hillsborough: A Southern Town in Prose and Poetry, Old Houses & Young Men: Notes on Renovation & Survival.
    - Notes and drafts, C-G, 1976-1979; 1989-1999; 2000-2004; undated; 50 folders (Box 15)
      Includes drafts and copies: Comfort; Communique; Competition; Complications; Concerned Baptist Novelist Appeals to Jesse Helms' Sense of Art; Dad's at the Office; A Dress is a Flag; Drown: How I Died and What I learned From It; Early Art and Notes; Eden: The Sequel; Essay: On Being Alone; Essential Stories Still Unwritten; Falls maps; Feels Like Home with Correspondence; Female Trouble; The Fertile 'We' of One Chaste 'I'; Fetch; First Week of His Retirement; The Food Obsession; The Fool of Quality or Heart in Hand The Fool of Quality; For the Norton Anthology: In Praise of Stephen Crane's 'The Open Boat'; Forced To: A Naughty Story for David Del Tredici; For the Memories; Friends Notes on Writing; The Future; Garden Sermon: Being the History of a History; Gatsby; and Gossip.
      - All Things Considered, 2004 Dec 24 (Box 72, Audio-cd RL11748-CD-0004)
        Includes Gurganus reading A Fool for Christmas.
    - Notes and drafts, G-M, 1984-1996; 2000-2008; undated; 48 folders (Box 16)
      Includes drafts and copies: Gossip; Gurganus on Melissa Meyer; Gurganus publicity biography; Having Come Out, Look! We Have Come Through: Or What Togs Are Appropriate For the March on Washington?; He's At the Office; The Henfield Prize Stories; Hiram Johnson Cuthrell Jr.: In Thanksgiving for His Life; House and Garden draft; How're the Folks; How I Died and What I Learned From It; How to Leave; In God There Is No East or West; In Praise of Stephen Crane's The Open Boat; Inside Out; Introduction of Gurganus by Ron George; The Invention of Suburbia; Inventory; Iowa drafts; I Sing in Praise of 'Man Bites Dog'; It Had Ears: Toward an Even More Precise Identification of the Newer Angels; John Cheever Turns 100; The Jubilee Dinner Program The Iowa Writers' Workshop; Lair and Refuge: I Work at Home, photographs by Frank Hunter; Legend Has It; The Lessons of Likeness; Lift Off, Laurel Wreaths and the Power of 'Yes': A Decade of the Henfield Prizes; Literary Outtakes: An Anecdote from Oldest Living Confederate Widow Tells All; Local Man for Granata; Love: An Introductory Offer; Luther's Dream; A Macho Fish Story for the Guy of Today; The Man with the Man that Drowned; Man, Woman, Dog, and a Hole in the Ground; The Man Who Loved Cemeteries; Many Happy Returns Inc.; Many Happy Returns of the Day Invocation, John One, One; Men are Either Loud or Silent; Mr. Barnhill Horse Rescue; and The Mortician Confesses.
      - Annotated proof, He's At the Office, undated (Box 23)
        Includes an oversized proof.
      - The Best American Short Stories, 2000 (Box 72, Audio-cd RL11748-CD-0003)
        Includes Gurganus reading He's at the Office.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, oversized, 1989 Jan 19 (Box 24)
        Includes Love at 99.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, undated (Box 23)
        Includes If Grandma Had Been Homer.
      - Proofs and galleys, published works, oversized, undated (Box 24)
        Includes Knopf Christmas Book List.
    - Notes and drafts, M, 1993; undated; 20 folders (Box 17)
      Includes drafts and copies: The Mortician Confesses; Mouth of the South; Museum; My Cultural Misappropriation; and My First Death.
    - Notes and drafts, M-T, 1973-1975; 1992-1999; 2000-2012; undated; 44 folders (Box 18)